Can you come off of testosterone
replacement therapy? If so, what
happens? This is an extremely nuanced
question, but the answer is yeah, it's
possible that you can come off of
testosterone replacement therapy after
you start it. Now, this is contingent on
a few things. First of all, were you
appropriately assessed? And if you were
appropriately assessed, what did your
FSH and or LH values look like prior to
starting testosterone replacement
therapy? Because if we have your FSH and
LH values, we can identify and thus
stratify you into whether or not you
have primary and or secondary
hypogonatism because that's a big factor
in indicating and defining if your balls
have the capability of making
testosterone. Again, another thing to
take into consideration is how much
testosterone were you even making before
getting on testosterone replacement? Cuz
let's be real, a lot of guys say that
they don't want to get on testosterone
because they're afraid it's going to
shut down their natural production.
Well, guess what? If your natural
production is 200, 250, you ain't making
anything anyway. So, I mean, you really
have nothing to shut down. Depending on
the underlying eeology,
then it's totally possible that you
could possibly come off. We've had guys
come off for whatever reason, whether
it's deployment, personal reasons,
whatnot. We've had guys come off and
have some degree of recovery. So, here's
something to think about. Let's say that
you start TRT at 30 and your
testosterone is 350. Now, you're 40
years old and you're considering coming
off for whatever reason. Cool. Okay.
Now, we know there's an age related
decline in your natural testosterone
levels. So, hypothetically, your 350 at
30 might now be 250 300 at your as your
new baseline untreated. So, you have to
take in consideration when you come off
if you're making testosterone, your new
industrious level is probably going to
be lower just cuz time is passed and
that's how life is. You make less as you
get older. Also, you have to take in
consideration how has your health
evolved from the time you started to the
time you decide to come off. So, let's
say that same person, they have a 350 at
age 30. Let's say now they're 40 and
they're on a few new medications.
They're on medications to treat lipids.
They're on a statin. Let's say they're
they have hypertension. They're on an
ACE inhibitor. Let's say they've also
gained 30 pounds. Well, we know they've
got an age related client that can
possibly contribute. And now they have
coorbidities to stack on top of that. So
that 350 at 30, they're now 40 year old
natural production might be 200 250 if
they're lucky considering that again age
related declines have occurred and
they've also accumulated some
coorbidities during this time frame.
Again, as you can see, this is an
extremely nuanced question. No one can
predict if you will produce testosterone
and no one can predict how much you will
if you do. But I'm speaking from what
I've seen clinically. I've worked with
numerous numerous guys, helped many of
guys come off of testosterone again for
whatever personal conviction or whatever
reason they do. And the vast majority of
them do recover their own natural
production. And the degree of recovery
tends to be within a deviation of their
pre-TRT levels, albeit with some age
related decline and/or health related
changes. So someone says starting TRT
means you're stuck on it for life.
That's not necessarily true. However,
one, you weren't making any in the first
place. That's why you got on TRT. And
two, who wants to go back to their
pre-TRT levels and feeling the way they
did?